Q: Can you describe the Four Noble Truths
that the Buddha teaches? Suffering, is
the First Noble Truth, there is suffering, second,
there is the cause of suffering. 3rd, cessation of
suffering and 4th, Path leading to the cessation of suffering.
A: Well, first and foremost,
they are 4 descriptions, or
four aspects of one insight, that insight being freedom
from suffering basically, feel free from suffering,
that already implies
the knowledge of what suffering is,
the knowledge of what has been causing
that suffering, that already implies the knowledge of freedom from suffering
and that already implies the knowledge of how to maintain, that freedom from suffering,
that insight.
Q: How to develop it?
A: well, how to maintain, which basically then
results in complete Liberation
from all the Upakkilesa and all the other kinds of pollution.
So it's not like 1, 2, 3, 4 that the person needs to discern
one by one,
basically, suffering and freedom from it.
And that's what many suttas mention
basically. It would only
talk about the cause of suffering.
Cause of suffering is, Nothing else except Craving
and that's again,
that's something that people might read over, and it seems like
it's making sense
of course
But actually, in terms of the direct insight,
seeing the craving is suffering
results in Liberation from that suffering
Seeing
the craving, means
abandoning the craving, so the only reason you crave, is
you don't really see it,
directly you don't understand it,
you haven't discerned it.
And
important aspect is to recognize that
whenever there is suffering present,
you can
induce correctly,
that the craving must be present
because suffering is there.
So it's not like, ''oh I suffer, now I have to look for the reason'', call it
craving or something else or also assuming that sometimes, something else
can be
the cause of your suffering.
Really needs to be brought down so narrowly
and so precisely
whereby you discern when the suffering,
the disagreeable
unpleasant feeling that you are resisting
basically, when the suffering is present,
means, it's because
simultaneously with it, there is craving present.
The absence of the craving, simultaneously means
the absence of that suffering,
there is no delay.
That's why
you can have the direct knowledge of freedom
from suffering, directly verified for yourself.
You cannot suffer amid suffering as the Buddha
would often say,
literally amid the things that used to make you suffer,
the mind cannot suffer now
because there is no more craving in regard to those
things.
Q: How to abandon craving?
A: How to abandon craving? Well, sense restraint,
Virtue, developed to the extent necessary, whereby you start
discerning then, your mental intentions,
whether they're rooted in wholesome
unwholesome, whether they're rooted in greed
aversion, delusion.
And when you know that they are,
you do not engage in them, you do not tolerate them, you do not
entertain them, you do not
proliferate them, you do not invest
in them.
That would basically enable the mind to then
Not resist the unpleasant
feeling, to Not indulge the pleasant
feeling, to Not try to distract yourself
from neutral feeling. And when mind stops doing
that, with the previous knowledge
that he's heard from outside through the suttas and
right teaching.
when mind stops
doing that,
with the previous knowledge of what craving is,
to be able to see, ''ah this is the absence of craving''
and he will be able to see right there, ''ah there is no suffering''
And then you'll be also able to understand what that
suffering was, even the suffering of the past.
Before he understood the way out,
he wouldn't be suffering on account of that either.
The same knowledge would be applied to
the present, past and future.
Q: How to endure those
painful feelings
you have them now?
A: You endure them
basically, instead of enduring,
you want to give in to sensuality
or you want to give in to ill-will or distraction.
Well, you don't do that.
Then, that would result in you having to endure them
but sometimes if you can,
you don't have to endure them
without having to give in to sensuality, aversion
or delusion
then, that's fine as well.
So you don't have to just constantly going
looking for pain, to endure
that wouldn't necessarily result in wisdom.
Q: Then how does one know if you're free
from craving?
A: Because there's no suffering amidst suffering. There is no suffering because you CANNOT suffer.
Not because you're hiding away from it
or because you're not
just avoiding things that used to
cause you to suffer, No.
Because avoiding things means you're afraid of something already.
A person doesn't leave
a kuti
then, they don't have to talk to anyone
because it might annoy them and then suffer.
So they aren't free from suffering,
they're just protecting their precarious environment
of non-disturbance.
But the fact that you must protect it,
means you're disturbed by that,
which means they're not truly Not suffering, they're just hiding away from the greater extent of it
So you want to recognize it.
That's why
Conscientious man doesn't neglect his duty, certain things that you must do,
they're not necessarily connected,
just sitting in solitude and practising
like here, we live by ourselves, we do things ourselves
so we have to go and fix the water line.
I don't have to,
but then I won't have any water.
But having to do that, doesn't bother you either.
You're not seeking out as a distraction,
but you're not running away from it
when it arises on its own
as something that's
necessary to be done to sustain the way you live in.
So you need to have again, that self-honesty,
So you know,
you're not hiding away.
You're not indulging,
you're not covering anything up, with that
self-honesty,
and restraint
of the senses, seeing the danger in slightest fault,
moderation in eating,
they'll result in
just obviously being mindful of your actions.
You start discerning mental Intentions, by discerning them
basically, mind is already developing certain perspective
because there is no craving without intention.
But there is intention without craving.
That's why Arahant still can intend and decide
and choose
but he has no craving.
But in order to see that, you have to see the intentions
to begin with,
most people are not even aware of the mental intentions.
They think intention is just the most obvious choice,
but it's not,
it's just little inclinations, thoughts in themselves
are already intentional.
So it's subtler, and in order to reach the subtler level,
this whole sense restraint, restrained by Patimokkha
by virtue, moderation
in eating, mindfulness, is absolutely necessary, not negotiable. And with right instructions, and right way of
looking, that's where the practice is.
Without the right instruction,
it is just restraint, which is good,
but it doesn't lead you to any knowledge, but with the right instruction and that, that's all
you need.
Because sometimes people might think,
OK, restraint is not the Dhamma, that's true
and then they'd think, ''Ok now, I got the Dhamma
so I don't have to restrain'', No.
Dhamma applies only where the restraint is.
So, you can see.
Yes, Restraint is not the Dhamma, as in the application of
dhamma, is not the same as the necessary basis
for the
application,
but you wouldn't be able to apply it
if there is no necessary basis.
And if the mind practises like that,
then, the inclination
in form of craving, is becoming more and more obvious.
Why? Because you start recognizing that certain ways
when you intend and incline,
makes you suffer, makes you feel too much, so to speak.
Makes you too involved, exposes you,
makes you liable,
by discerning those things, you stop intending like that.
By not intending like that, you're not perpetuating
the craving.
Q: In terms of feelings?
A: Yes, of course, it's always in relation to feelings.
So in an agreeable feeling, that
is present,
you have to
discern the inclination
towards wanting more of it
or towards wanting to stay longer,
towards wanting to not go away soon,
towards wanting to increase it,
to intensify it, to prolong it,
any of those things. In a disagreeable feeling,
be the general disagreeable mood or something
more specific,
you have to remove (the inclination)
or rather discern, and by discerning you
remove it automatically, inclination towards resisting it.
Towards trying to find the justification for it.
Towards trying to find an explanation for it,
towards psychologizing it.
just any of those
things are mechanism
which you're trying to engage in, so to remove it, get rid of it.
And the subtlest of them is neutral feeling
when it's neither pleasant nor unpleasant.
And that's when people give into distraction, delusion,
indolence, laziness,
mental heedlessness.
So if you don't do any of those 3 things,
you're not perpetuating craving.
Q: And at the same time
you could be able to
feel, to be aware of your feelings.
A: Yes, of course, to the extent they have arisen on their own.
because feelings arise, having arisen, they cease on their own,
you have no
say in that.
That's what mindfulness of feeling is,
discerning the nature, basically.
Knowing that they have arisen on their own
this pleasant experience at the moment, arisen on its own basically.
That's fine.
You try to get rid of it because pleasure is craving? No, it doesn't. Leaning too much
towards that pleasure,
means craving,
leaning away from the disagreeable, means craving.
Leaning towards forgetfulness
and distraction
means craving, in the neutral feeling.
Q: So being aware of those leanings towards feelings is the way?
A: Yes, that's a good way to start.
You can't be having, ''oh this is my craving''
Craving is in your attitude,
but you can bring it down so precisely
whereby you'd see either
the presence of suffering or the presence of
the possibility to suffer.
Any of those is generated by the
amount of your leaning
You're automatically generating
possible liability to suffering,
which is in itself, dukka.
So you use that, to know whether you lean or not
Recognition of how liable to suffering
does this make you.
Q: There is no method that can show you that.
A: Of course not. Because method is on the level of
almost like bodily action or certainly
bodily perceptions that
you're perceiving or going through
some motions. We're talking about intentions behind your actions.
So whatever the method you do
you have to look at intention behind, which means method becomes redundant
which means method is your Sila.
Method is your sense restraint,
that is closest method as you can get.
Method is your moderation in eating.
Q: There's no point in
noting every movement of your mind, quickly write it down?
A: It's completely misplaced, looking in the wrong place.
Because you're not seeing
your intention to note.
You couldn't be noting your intention to note.
Noting is an action which is already intended
which is already leaned towards,
and you're not seeing that.
By not seeing that, no amount
of engaging in that action reveals its nature, otherwise Buddha
would have given the method and described in the suttas, when they did ask him what was the direct method,
he said, ''a young man, develops faith, leaves
his home, lives
restrained by the rules of Patimokkha, practises
sense restraint,
sees the danger in the slightest fault
moderation in eating,
and devotes his time basically to wakefulness.
First Watch of the night, 2nd watch of the night, 3rd watch of the night. then he understands rebirth has been destroyed.
And I remember first time I read as a layman,
I was also looking for a method, and I thought this was too general,
why wouldn't he give you
a particular recipe, how to become enlightened? Because there isn't any. This is the most particular
you can get, if you are not seeing it in a direct matter
just because of all the wrong views that are on top of it.
So you need to meet that Buddha's instruction
halfway basically, or even two-thirds of the way to
start to make sense.
but if a person don't change any of you
and then they just add on top of their views, their notion of their practices, that's what you can get. Methods and modern Vipassana technique,
or methods of concentration and so on
No, you have to look at intention behind action
so you can't concentrate on that,
because it's behind your concentration.
You can discern it, you can know it.
That's why it says
the consciousness is to be fully understood.
Not concentrated on.
Q: So you can't be aware of your Intentions?
A: You can be aware, in that peripheral background manner, but awareness and concentration in terms of techniques
is not the same thing.
People are not aware
when they do meditation techniques, quite opposite, they're practising some sort of
focusing exercises on one thing or the other,
which means there's no general awareness there.
Q: To be able to see your intentions?
A: They can only be seen indirectly.
Q: By the way you are,
whatever you're choosing,
A: They can only be seen indirectly
on the basis of sense restraint and sila.
You can't see them indirectly if you are unrestrained.
Q: If you are not restrained by keeping sila?
A: You can have a notion of it, to some extent
but understanding the Nature, having that clarity
generated to the point of being able to
fully discern it,
you won't have that.
It is just like trying to collect the water
in 10 meter deep pool, tank
we just constantly punching hole in the bottom of it.
So it'll never fill up to the top.
And you need to have
it filled up
basically.